<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A prognostication made for y[e] yeere of our Lorde God 1566 declaryng the chau[n]ge, full, &amp; quarters of the moone, w[ith] other,accustomable matters, seruing all England / by Maister F. Cox ...</title>
            <author>Coxe, Francis, fl. 1560.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 431.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S23</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21469024</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21469024</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24018</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24018)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1738:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A prognostication made for y[e] yeere of our Lorde God 1566 declaryng the chau[n]ge, full, &amp; quarters of the moone, w[ith] other,accustomable matters, seruing all England / by Maister F. Cox ...</title>
                  <author>Coxe, Francis, fl. 1560.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[29] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted [at London?] at the long shop adioining vnto S. Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie by John Alde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1566]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 5949.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and torn, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ephemerides.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſtication made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeere of our Lorde God. 566. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claryng the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, Full, &amp; Quarters of the Moone, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other, accuſtomable mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, ſeruing all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. By Maiſter. F. Cox. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprynted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Londo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at the long Shop adioining vnto S. Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie by Iohn Alde.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="almanac">
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:2"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of the Eclipſe.</head>
               <p>THis yeere the .xxviii. day of October at. v. of the clocke. xxxv. minutes after noone ſhal appere an Eclipſe If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moone and ſhalbe darckened, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iii. poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Although that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>pſe of the Sun, or Moone be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Philoſophicallye rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons may be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> while it ſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceth: yet notwithſtandi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I wiſhe the louing reader to take aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſment by this and other moſte ſtraunge impreſſions ſéene of late in the ayre to flée from ſin, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the world almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> where ſwarmeth. For vndoubtid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe terrible tenmpeſts, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome ſéene ſights do preache vnto
<pb facs="tcp:24018:3"/> vs gods forathfull indignation to be euen at our doores (if we ſpede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly repent not) vtterly to deſtroye vs. What wunderfull ſightꝭ were ſene at Ieruſalem before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction therof: Ioſephus doth teſtify, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> people tooke no regarde the run to but ſtill per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuered in theyr moſte filthye and vngodly liues: God at laſt perfor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mid that he had thretnid and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyed them executyng on them the rod of his Iuſtice and terible indignation, which toke no regar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to his ſwéet and fatherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition Deſerte not therfore the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> returne, put not of repentance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daye to day, leaſt that whileſt you ſo diſſemble with your duble hartꝭ, god vtterly tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb facs="tcp:24018:3"/> away his face &amp; when ye wold there be no place leſt vnto you to repent, as of late dayes within the countie of Suſſex we haue had a-moſte terrible exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in one that dyed moſte lamentablye deſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe in the mercies of God. Of whome I purpoſe god willyng to ſet out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ſtory, or rather mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte fearfull tragedye to this ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that we beholdi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſeuere Iuſtice of almightie god, in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> partie: may learne to ſhake of our vyle carnal ſecurytie and after the councel of Chriſte to watche with prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="winter" type="season">
               <head>¶ Of Wynter, the firſt part of the yere. Criii,</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:4"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>¶ Hyems, omnium conſenſu, frigida et humida dicitur, non tamen ea de cauſa, quod reliquis temporibus frigidior h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>or<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſit, ſed quod frigiditas in to ſuperat caliditurem, et humiditas ſiccitatem.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WInter beginneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xii. day of Decembre when the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> entreth in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt degree of Capricorne whiche day is the ſhorteſt day in the yere for then is the ſunne fardeſt of from vs. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginneth the day to encrece agai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne and the night to decrece. This parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yéere by nature is colde and moyſte and therfore the diſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes that happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this parte of the yéere ar colde and moyſt diſeaſes, as Coughes, Rewmes, Horſneſſe Goutꝭ Fluxes. &amp;c. This time of the
<pb facs="tcp:24018:4"/> yéere ſhall the Cholericke parſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be in beſt lyking. In this quarter of the yéere as teſtefieth. Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. 1. Aphor. 15. We ought to eate muche and to drinke little and to eat thoſe meatꝭ as ar hote and dry of complexio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. as ar Cunnies, Pigi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and all ſmal byrdꝭ. &amp;c. This time meatꝭ roſted are more hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome then ſod.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="spring" type="season">
               <head>¶ Of Ver or Spring tyme.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Ver ſaluberimum eſt, minime<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> morbis qui mortem afferani, obnoxium.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>VEr begynneth the .xii. of Marche when the Sunne entreth into the firſte mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of Aries, then is the day and
<pb facs="tcp:24018:5"/> night equal. This quarter of the yéere after the minde of ſome is hot &amp; moyſt, but after the mynde of Hippocrates &amp; Galene it is tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and therfore is the moſt hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt parte of the yéere. In this parte of the yéere I councel thoſe to be let blood who doubt them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be vexed with any ſickneſſe the reſt of the yéere after, for by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meanes ſhall helth be preſeruid. The diſſeaſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> happen this quar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of the yéere do moſte commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly procéed of blood and ſuperfluity of moyſture, as Pleureſies, Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Blodye flyres, Scabbes, Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and ſuche lyke. The ſanguin this time of the yéere ſhall proſper and ſo ſhal the Melancholick alſo. This time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yéere muſt we eate
<pb facs="tcp:24018:5"/> leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we did in winter &amp; drink ſomthing more and alſo vſe more ſodd meatꝭ then roſted and alſo ſuche meatꝭ as are nuriſhing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="summer" type="season">
               <head>¶ Of Sommer.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>¶ Eſtas calida et ſicca criſtit.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>SOmmer begineth the .xiii. day of Iune at what tyme the Sunne entreth in to Cancer. that daye is the longeſt day in all the yéere. The Sommer by nature is hot &amp; drye, his diſſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes procede of Choler &amp; blood, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hot burnyng Agues, Quotidia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Tertians. This parte of the yéer, ſhall the Flegmaticke complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be in beſt lyking. In this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:24018:6"/> we ought to eate lytle and to drinke muche and thoſe meatꝭ we eat: ought to be ſodde meatꝭ and of colde complexion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="autumn" type="season">
               <head>¶ Of Autumne.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>¶ Autumnus inequalis eſt.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AVtumne beginneth the xiiii. of September whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſunne entreth into Libra then is the day and night e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall. This parte of the yéere is the moſt vnholſomeſt parte, and is diſtemperid in complexion, and therfore is callid the nurice of all diſſeaſes. This time we ought to vſe good &amp; holſome diete and to eat more then we did in ſommer and alſo to drinke leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:6"/>
               <head>¶ Of Sickeneſſe that ſhal happen this yéere.</head>
               <p>IN the Spryng time of this yéere and Winter alſo ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be many daungerouſe and greuouſe ſickneſſes as Pleureſies paine in the Lungꝭ. Feuers, Verti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gines, Falling ſickneſſe Rumes, Apoplexie, Madnes, Iaundyes, Leproſie, Vlcers, Byles, Ache in the Iointꝭ &amp; ſuche like. The Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time and Autumne ſhal bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hot feuers, as Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ice et Erratice, w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptions Cholick, Stra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with other great obſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; putrefactions. Let vs therfore make our praiers vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternall god to geue vs grace to amende our liues and to flée from ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:24018:7"/> that we béeing turnid from our wickedneſſes, he may alſo turne him frome the plages wherwith he hath deuiſed to puniſhe vs. Pray therfore continualye. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ For blood letting.</head>
               <p>¶ I found in a litle book intituled (Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus medico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. concerning blood letti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as foloweth The firſt day of the Moon, is meetly good. The ſecond &amp; third euel, the iiii v. vj vij viij. and ninth euel. the .x. but meetly good the .xi. is meetly good for yung men hauing need The xij. good the xiij. meetly good. xiiij. &amp; xv. euel. xvi. &amp;. xvij. meetly good xviij good for yung me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be choleric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for olde men xix. and. xx. euel .xxi. good. xxii. very good, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxiij. xxiiii xxv and. xxvi. good. xxvij. euel. xxviii and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> xxix. euel, the .xxx. wurs.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="almanac">
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:7"/>
            <head>¶ The diſpoſition of the we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther in the .xij. Monethes of the yeere.</head>
            <div n="January" type="month">
               <head>¶ Ianuary.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a group sitting at an indoor table</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ful Moone the .v. day at .ix. of the clock .xi minutes after noon clowdy, wynde Northerly.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter the .xiii. day at viii. of the clock in the morning, raine and winde.</p>
               <p>The new Moone the .xxi. day at
<pb facs="tcp:24018:8"/> x. of the .clock in the morning. ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable for the tyme of the yeere.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the .xxviii. day at. iii. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock after noone, raine with ſome froſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="February" type="month">
               <head>¶ February.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a group sitting by a fire</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ful Moone the .iiii day at. i, of the clock. xxxi. minutes before noone raine winde ſoutheaſt.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter the .xii. day at ii. of the clock in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, froſt after rayn with ſleet.</p>
               <p>The new Moone the .xix day
<pb facs="tcp:24018:8"/> xi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock. xx. minutꝭ after noon rain, ſleet, hayle and bluſteringe wyndes.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the .xxvi. day at. x. of the clock after noone, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to moiſture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="March" type="month">
               <head>¶ Marche.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two men planting seeds</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ful Moone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. v. day at xi. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock after noon, rain, wind ſouth.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter the .xiiij. day at. i. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, winde.</p>
               <p>The new moone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxi. day at. xi.
<pb facs="tcp:24018:9"/> of the clock before noone, bluſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wether after inclined to moi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſture.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the .xxviii. day at one of the clock in the morning faire wether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="April" type="month">
               <head>¶ Apryl.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of two men scaring birds</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll moone the .iiij. day at. ij of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clock after noon ſome ſweet ſhowers.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xij. day at v. of the clock in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> afternoon, faire.</p>
               <p>The new Moone the .xix. day and
<pb facs="tcp:24018:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> vii. of the clock after noone, faire, after inclined to moiſture.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the .xxvi day at. x. of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> clock before noone raine</p>
            </div>
            <div n="May" type="month">
               <head>¶ Maye.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a group sitting at an outdoor table while one plays a standing stringed instrument</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The full moone the .iiij. day at vi. of the clock in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> morning raine and winde northeaſt.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter the .xii. day at viii. of the clock before noone, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to raine and miſt</p>
               <p>The new moone the .xix. day at
<pb facs="tcp:24018:10"/> iii. of the clock in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, faire wether winde weſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the xxv. day at x. of the clock after noone faire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="June" type="month">
               <head>¶ Iune</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man and woman shearing sheep</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ful Moone the .ii. day at. ix. of the clock after noone, clowdy.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarter the .x. day at. vi of the clock after noone faire and temperat whether.</p>
               <p>The new Moone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. xvii. day at. x
<pb facs="tcp:24018:10"/> of the clock before noone, miſtye, inclined to wynde.</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the .xxiiii. day at. x. of the clock before noone, fair wether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="July" type="month">
               <head>¶ Iuly.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a group cutting hay with a scythe and stacking it</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The ful Moone the ſecond day at xi. of the clock before noone faire.</p>
               <p>The laſt quarte. x. day at, ii of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, ſome moiſture.</p>
               <p>The new moone the .xvi. day at vii. of the clock after noone, faire.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The firſt quarter the .xxiii. day at. i. of the clock before noon faire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="August" type="month">
               <head>¶ Auguſt.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a group standing in a field of tall corn or wheat</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The full Moone the firſt day at x. of the clock in the morning ſom thing diſpoſed to moiſture.</p>
               <p>The laſt puarter the .viii day at x. of the clock before noone, fayre wether.</p>
               <p>The new Moone the .xv. day at iiii, of the clock in the morning, ſome raine and muche winde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The fyrſt quarter the .xxii. day at vii, of the clock after noon faire.</p>
               <p>The ful moone the .xxx, day at ii of the clock after noone</p>
            </div>
            <div n="September" type="month">
               <head>¶ September.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man sowing seeds</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The laſt quarter the .vi day at. ii of the clock after noone fayre,</p>
               <p>The new moone the .xiii, day a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ii, of the clock after noone fayre,</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the xxi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> xi, of the clock, l, ninutes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> noone, diſpoſed to rayne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:12"/>
               <p>The ful Moone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxix. dai at. iiii of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, fair wether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="October" type="month">
               <head>¶ October.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man rolling barrels</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The laſt quarter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> v. day at. vi of the clock after noone, raine,</p>
               <p>The new moone the xiii. day at iii. of the clock in the morni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g faire</p>
               <p>The firſt quarter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee xxi. day at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the clock in the morning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>d to raine,</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul Moone the xxviii, day at
<pb facs="tcp:24018:12"/> v. of the clock after noone, raine,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="November" type="month">
               <head>¶ Nouember.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a group cutting and gathering wood</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The laſt quarter the iiii, day art v, of the clock before noone fayre</p>
               <p>The new moone the xii day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the clock in the fore noone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt quarter the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> one of the clocke in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> darke and gloomy we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>The ful moone the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ii, of the clocke in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Haile and ſtormye wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="December" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ December.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man and woman working outdoors</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>The laſt quarter the iii, day at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the clock after noone, faire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> new moone y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, xi, day at, iii, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lock in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after noone, faire, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt quarter, xix day at, v.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> after noone faire, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oinde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one the xxvi, day at .i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fter noone dark &amp; gloo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſpoſed to ſnowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_fairs">
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:13"/>
            <head>¶ Here folow the principall thorow out England kept euery Fairee Moneth in the yeere.</head>
            <div n="January" type="month">
               <head>¶ January.</head>
               <p>The. vt. day at Saliſbury. &amp; at Briſtowe the .xv. day at Briſtow and at Chirching ford.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="February" type="month">
               <head>¶ February.</head>
               <p>The ſecond day at Bathe, at Maide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone The 14. at Feuerſham. A ſhewedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day at Lichefeelde, Roiſton &amp; Tamworth The 24. at Henly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Themmes and at Teuxbury.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="March" type="month">
               <head>¶ Marche,</head>
               <p>The firſt monday in Lent at Ciceſter at Abingdon. The 4. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day in Lent at Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ford &amp; at Sudbery. The 5. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day at Grantha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The monday before our Lady day at Salyſ-bury, on Palm ſunday euen at Wiſbiche &amp; at Kendall. The 13. Wie. The midlent Sunday at the Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ſo to Bodman, on Palm ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day at Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fret &amp; at worceſter. The. 20. day at Durha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The. 25 at Northampton, at Walton at great Chart, at Newcaſtel at Huntingto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; all the Lady dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="April" type="month">
               <pb facs="tcp:24018:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ April.</head>
               <p>The. 5. day at wallingford. The 7. at Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. The. 9. at Bickelſworth, at Billing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth. The monday after at Eueſham. The 3. Sunday after Eaſter at Lowoth. The. 23. day at Ipſwich, at Amtil, at Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningham, Gilford and at S. Pombes in Cornwall, The 25. at Darby, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 26. at Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terden.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="May" type="month">
               <head>¶ May.</head>
               <p>The 1. day at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erm in Cornwall. at Stow the olde, at Reding, at Leceſter, at Maidſtone, at Chelmeſford. The 8 day at Beuerlay. Aſſention day at Newcaſtel, at Yarne, at Brimingham, at S. Edes at Biſhop ſtandford, at Banbury, Beckha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feeld, and Storford. On whit ſunday at Rie hil, at Cribby and at Kingſton vpon Themes. On the teweſday at Lewis. On Trinitie euen at Stokeſly at Kendal. On Trinitie Sunday at S Mary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uke at Rowel, on whitſon monday at Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington, at Excetur, at Bradford on the Tewſday at Lewes. The 29 day at Cram<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brook. The 27. day at Lenham.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="June" type="month">
               <head>¶ June.</head>
               <p>On Thurſday next after Trinitie Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
<pb facs="tcp:24018:14"/> at Banbury, at Storford, at S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, at Newbery. at Couentrie, at S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es at Biſhop Standford, &amp; at Roſſe, the. 9 day at Maidſton, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 11. at Okigham, The 23 at Shreweſbury &amp; S Albanes. Midſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mmer day at Bedel, Staſtoke S. Annes and at wakefeeld. The 24. at Cranbroke, Gloceſter, at Lin at Winſor, Cambridge and at Harriſam, The 26. at wolleth, and Peterborow, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 27. at Folkſtone. On Sai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Peters dai at wadhurſt, marlborow, Holſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth. Northampton &amp; Peterborow. The 24 at Hariſam. The 28. at Hetcorne and at Pombes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="July" type="month">
               <head>¶ July.</head>
               <p>The 7. day at Rychmund in the North, at Topelit at Canterbury, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 11. Horſfayre at partney, at F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abor and at Felix. the. 12. at Lid, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 16. at Pinchbeck y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 17. at Winche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>combe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 24 at Vxbridge &amp; Cateſby, the 22 at Barnades Caſtle at Magdalene, and at Otly. the 23. at Marlborow, at wincheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Colcheſter, Tedbery. 25 at briſtow, Do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer, Chilham, Ipſwiche Northampton, Darby. S. Iames by London, Reding, at Lowth, Maulmeſbury &amp; Thirſby, the 26. at Dankeſter, Poglington the olde and
<pb facs="tcp:24018:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> at Thropſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="August" type="month">
               <head>¶ Auguſt.</head>
               <p>The 1. day at Exceter. Feuerſham, Dun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtable. S Edes-at Bedford, at Marham churche at Wiſbiche &amp; at York, the. 9. at Romney, the 10. at Laurence wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am, at Hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerford, Bedford. Strods, at Blacka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, at S. Laurence, at Bodma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Mol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton, at Bedford and at Farnam, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. 11. day at Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bredge. The 24 at London at Terox bury at Sudbery, at Norwiche, at North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampton, at Douer and at Rie, the. 28. at Aſheford.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="September" type="month">
               <head>¶ September.</head>
               <p>The 8. at Wakefeeld, Sturbridge fair at Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bridg at London in Southwark. at Suide, at R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>coluer, at Eiſboron, both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lady daies, at Partney. iii. Lady daies, The 14. at Richemund in the North, at Rippon Penhall, at Berſley, at Waltain abbey at Wutton vnder Hedge, at Wen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>douer, &amp; at Smaldig. The 21. at Marlbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, at Bedford, at Croido<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. at Hulden in Huldernes. at S. Edmonds Bury at Malton, at. S Ines, at Hadley, at Lana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at Miltmal, at Siningborne, at Douer and at Eſtay The 29. at Stamdrop, at Malton horſfair, at way hil, at Newbery,
<pb facs="tcp:24018:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> at Leceſter &amp; at La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terbery, S. Deniſe day at Harborow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="October" type="month">
               <head>¶ October.</head>
               <p>The 4. day at Michel the 6. at S. Siths beſide Norwiche. The 13. at Graueſend, at Winfore, at Marchefeeld at Ely at S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aneton, at Charing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 18. at Vpan, at T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riſt. The 21. at Saffran walde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> The. 28 at Newmarket, at Hertforde, at Liceter, the. 30. at Stokeſly, at Bridge north, on S Lukes day</p>
            </div>
            <div n="November" type="month">
               <head>¶ Nouember.</head>
               <p>The 1. day at wakefeeld, The 2. at at Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chingly, the 6 at Newporryo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; at Sta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ley, the 10 at Lenton beſide Notingha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the 11. at Marlborow, at Douer The. 13. at S. Edmundes very, the. 20. at Heth, at Ingarſtone, the 23. at Sandwich. The 30. at Coligborow, at Rocheſter, at Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, vi. at Tregny in Cornwal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="December" type="month">
               <head>¶ December.</head>
               <p>The v day at Plukely The vi, at Spal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and at Exceter. The ſeueth at Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hurſt The xxix. at Canterbury.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis. ⁋</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24018:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
